and now we have seen raid 0 1 2
there is a 3 but we didn't see it 4 and
5 is there such a thing as raid 6. yes
there is
it's similar to raid 5 except that each
group of blocks instead of getting one
parity block
gets two
let's call them parity quoted blocks
they have different types of parity
and as a result rate six can work when
there are two failed stripes per group
note that we cannot do this with two
parity blocks one of the blocks that we
keep extra one of the non-data blocks is
going to be the real parity block and
that's what fixes one error
the second of the two blocks is a
different type of check blocks
and when only one disk has failed we use
the parity to recover but when two disks
have failed we can still solve some
equations where the data and the two
types of check blocks figure so that we
can still recover the content of the two
failed disks
so let's compare raid 5 and raid 6. raid
6 has twice the overhead of raid 5. so
we pay twice as much for the increased
reliability
there is more right overhead because
really now when we update a data block
we need to read and write the data block
and both
of the check blocks the parity and the
second one are also read and written so
there are now six
axises per right
versus four per right that we had with
rate five so the only reason for having
grade 6 if there is a good chance of
when a disk fails another one failing
before we manage to replace the first
fail drive so note that in any of the
raid configurations
once your disk fails you don't keep
going
and ignore the fail drive you keep going
but you order a replacement or get a
replacement and install it so that the
raid array can re-establish itself after
that you can lose another disk so really
rate six with its ability to lose
two disks
only helps if when a disk fails
there is a good chance of another
failing
before the first one is replaced the
faster we replace the first drive the
less chance there is that another disk
fails during that period of time
remember that the probability of a disk
failing during an hour is extremely low
so even if we spend something like three
days replacing a disk
the probability of a disk failing in
that specific time while we are
vulnerable is very very low and then it
seems that raid six is an overkill